<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science Portfolio on José Gouveia</title>
    <link>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Science Portfolio on José Gouveia</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 10:58:08 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Data Visualization: Inequality of COVID-19 Vaccinations</title>
      <link>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-8_vaccinationscovid/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 10:58:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-8_vaccinationscovid/</guid>
      <description>As developed countries head for booster shots, a rising concern on the inequality of COVID-19 vaccines distributions is coming to surface. Is this concern, however, exaggerated?
Percentage of People Fully Vaccinated   Source: Our World in Data Well… It’s not. As Portugal nears 75% of full vaccination rates on its population, there are still countries not reaching 1%. Perhaps unsurprisingly, African countries rate among the worse, as only 3% of the continent’s population is fully vaccinated against COVID-19.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing a Trading Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-7_prestigealgo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 10:58:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-7_prestigealgo/</guid>
      <description>The Project: By late 2020, a close friend of mine asked for help implementing a trading strategy he had thought of. I eagerly accepted the challenge. I can’t say, however, that I expected it to be extremely profitable. His idea was so simple, it was difficult to believe that it would fare well in a market filled with sophisticated trading algorithms. But, well.. it turned out to do just that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master Thesis</title>
      <link>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-1_master_thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 10:58:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-1_master_thesis/</guid>
      <description>Motivation: Have you ever had the curiosity to understand how Donald Trump’s election affected the US’ stock market? More specifically, have you ever wondered how it impacted environmentally responsible and carbon-intensive firms?
My thesis focused on answering such questions. The stock market reactions to the below three events were studied:
• Donald Trump’s election in 2016
• The nomination of Scott Pruitt to lead the Environmental Protection Agency
• The Withdrawal of the U.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Oil and Gold Prices - ARIMA Model</title>
      <link>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-5_suriname/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 11:15:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-5_suriname/</guid>
      <description>Motivation: What are the prospects of investing in Suriname for an international investor? How has the development of prices and exchange rates been in this country? And how can we predict its development? Understanding Suriname’s economic outlook and development is the main goal of the project. This country’s economy, however, is highly dependent on gold and oil price shifts, so understanding the development of these commodities prices could give us insights on the prior.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Employee Attrition</title>
      <link>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-3_attrtion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2019 11:13:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-3_attrtion/</guid>
      <description>The problem: IFM Healthcare’s employee attrition rate was at 15%, almost twice the industry’s benchmark rate. Given high attrition levels could bring all sort of costs to the firm, an employee retention plan was put in place. For the solution design, we were given a budget of $1M to implement the salary raise policy, with the following insight: a 20% salary increase would reduce the probability of attrition to 0. The goal was to target the most productive employees that had also higher chances to leave the firm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Event Study Framework</title>
      <link>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-2_eventstudy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2019 11:00:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-2_eventstudy/</guid>
      <description>Motivation: Oftentimes, certain extremely unexpected events can&amp;rsquo;t but shake a market as it is: Brexit, the Panama papers release, Donald Trump&amp;rsquo;s election in 2016, to name a few&amp;hellip; How can we study the impact of such events on the valuation of firms directly involved in these situations?
In this notebook, I aim to present a guide on how to perform an event study, using Python. More specifically, I provide a framework on how to compute Capital Asset Pricing Model (CAPM) adjusted returns, which is a measure widely used academically to perform such studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web Scraping the Magic Formula Website</title>
      <link>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-6_magicformula_webscrapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 10:58:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlbgouveia.github.io/jose_portfolio/post/project-6_magicformula_webscrapping/</guid>
      <description>Motivation: For a general use, if you want to keep track of information on a website that you have an account on, and periodically receive an email with an excel file with that same information, then this notebook should serve as the basis to do that job.
The Process: In this project in particular, I use Python to automate the following actions:
• Going to the Magic Formula Investing Website, and perform a login with my account</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
